Shavua tov שבוע טוב Shavua tov everybody.
Welcome to the post-Tisha B'Av תשעה באב Tisha B'Av period. Today's daf
דף daf what we're picking up today is Ayin Heh Amud Bet
ע"ה עמוד ב', Ayin Heh Amud Bet, 75B. And we start where
it is Masnisa מתניתין, Masnisa, where is it? The Gemara גמרא Gemara
says, we're in the middle of discussing the question about Modeh B'Knas
v'Achar Kach Ba'u Eidim מודה בקנס ואחר כך באו עדים, Modeh B'Knas
v'Achar Kach Ba'u Eidim,
where are we exactly?
Nine lines down from very good, Brayta d'Tanya ברייתא דתניא. Brayta d'Tanya.
Okay, Brayta d'Tanya ברייתא דתניא, Brayta d'Tanya, line starts with Dumya d'Apei
d'Chad דומיא דאפי דחד. Dumya d'Apei d'Chad. Okay,
so we've had three opinions now, or two opinions and a variation.
The opinions are: Rav רב Rav says that if you admit to
a Knas קנס Knas and eidim עדים eidim come afterwards, you remain
exempt. Your admission not only doesn't obligate you but it exempts you.
Shmuel שמואל Shmuel says no, if you admit you're not obligated but
if witnesses come afterwards you do become obligated. The Gemara גמרא Gemara
really comes, seems very much to come down in favor of Rav
רב, Rav, that your admission actually exempts you. But then there's an
opinion that nuances it and says: what type of an admission exempts
you if witnesses come later? That's only admission that Chiyev Atzmo B'Keren
חייב עצמו בקרן, Chiyev Atzmo B'Keren, that through your admission you actually
obligated yourself in a principal. That's a real admission. But if your
admission only had the effect of relating to the Knas קנס Knas
and therefore it would only exempt you, then it does not have
the ability to exempt. So no admission ever obligates you, but the
claim is that according to Rav רב, Rav, the admission that would
exempt you would be one that would obligate you in a Keren
קרן, Keren, that your own admission makes you pay a principal and
therefore you get, you're exempt even if witnesses come later from any
additional Knas קנס. Knas. So we're trying to demonstrate that support for
that position. So one support we had was from the Mishna משנה
Mishna and now we pick up from this first support from the
Brayta ברייתא. Brayta. Brayta d'Tanya ברייתא דתניא, Brayta d'Tanya, you can support
this from the Brayta ברייתא Brayta because we talked. Ro'eh eidim she-memashmashin
u-va'in רואה עדים שממשמשין ובאין, Ro'eh eidim she-memashmashin u-va'in, so this is
the Brayta ברייתא Brayta we saw the other day. You saw witnesses
that were like moving on their way in the process of coming
to Beis Din בית דין Beis Din and you decided you were
going to beat them out. They were going to come anyway so
you might as well just admit to it. So ve-amar ganaf'ti ואמר
גנבתי ve-amar ganaf'ti and you said yes I burgled aval lo tavachti
v'lo macharti אבל לא טבחתי ולא מכרתי, aval lo tavachti v'lo macharti,
I did not do the slaughtering or the selling. Eino meshalem ela
keren אינו משלם אלא קרן, eino meshalem ela keren, you only pay
the principal. The Chiddush חידוש Chiddush of that Mishna משנה Mishna is
that even though you see the witnesses about to come, it's still
considered an admission. So even though you only did it because you
were afraid of them, it's an admission and even if they come
afterwards, you're not going to pay the Kefel כפל, Kefel, you already
admitted. So that's a clear proof to Rav רב Rav that even
if you admitted and the witnesses came later, you're not going to
pay the, you remain exempt from the Knas קנס, Knas, exempt from
the Kefel כפל. Kefel. And the reason you're not going to pay
the four and the five, it's great, like you didn't even have
to admit to the four and the five, you could deny it,
but once you're not paying the Kefel כפל, Kefel, so four and
part of the four and five is the Kefel כפל, Kefel, so
therefore you're not going to pay the four and the five either.
Okay, that's the Chiddush חידוש Chiddush of the Brayta ברייתא. Brayta. Now
how does it, how is it a support to this idea? So
the Gemara גמרא Gemara says like this. Ram'li limis'na רמי
לי למיתנא, Ram'li limis'na, why does it the example in the Brayta
ברייתא Brayta is given ve-amar ganaf'ti ואמר גנבתי, ve-amar ganaf'ti, you admit
that you burgled, aval lo tavachti v'lo macharti אבל לא טבחתי ולא
מכרתי, aval lo tavachti v'lo macharti, you didn't admit to the tevicha
u-mechira טביחה ומכירה. tevicha u-mechira. Nis'nei ניתני, Nis'nei, why doesn't it give
an example o ganaf'ti או גנבתי, o ganaf'ti, either you admit to
the Gneivah גניבה Gneivah and then you get off even if the
witnesses come from the Kefel כפל Kefel and then automatically from the
four and the five, o tavachti macharti או טבחתי ומכרתי o tavachti
macharti or you only admitted to the tevicha mechira טביחה ומכירה tevicha
mechira and then you would get off on the tevicha mechira טביחה
ומכירה tevicha mechira if the witnesses come. Why don't you give either
example? So it must be that the second example isn't true. Elah
ha kama'shmalan אלא הא קמשמע לן, Elah ha kama'shmalan, one minute, Elah
ha kama'shmalan אלא הא קמשמע לן, Elah ha kama'shmalan, it's teaching you
time d'amar ganaf'ti דאמר גנבתי, d'amar ganaf'ti, the reason your admission exempts
you even if the witnesses come after is because you admitted to
the basic
Gneivah גניבה. Gneivah. Okay, d'chiyev atzmo b'keren דחייב עצמו בקרן, d'chiyev atzmo
b'keren, because then you obligated yourself at least in the principal. That's
a case d'patur דפטור. d'patur. Aval lo ganaf'ti אבל לא גנבתי, aval
lo ganaf'ti, if you denied the Gneivah גניבה Gneivah u-va v'amar v'eidim
d'ganvum ובא ואמר ועדים דגנבום, u-va v'amar v'eidim d'ganvum, the witnesses said
you were ganav גנב ganav v'chazar v'amar tavachti macharti וחזר ואמר טבחתי
ומכרתי, v'chazar v'amar tavachti macharti, if you only had admitted to the
tevicha mechira טביחה ומכירה, tevicha mechira, in that case this law wouldn't
be correct, you wouldn't be exempt u-va'u eidim she-tavach u-machar ובאו עדים
שטבח ומכר u-va'u eidim she-tavach u-machar since your admission to the tevicha
mechira טביחה ומכירה tevicha mechira after there's already been eidim עדים eidim
to the Gneivah גניבה Gneivah is not obligating yourself in anything in
that case, chayav חייב, chayav, the witnesses would obligate you. Alma אלמא,
Alma, so the fact that it gives the example that your admission
exempts you in that you admitted to the Gneivah גניבה Gneivah and
doesn't give the example that you admitted to the tevicha mechira טביחה
ומכירה, tevicha mechira, you see it's exactly what we're trying to say.
Hoda'at tevicha lav hoda'ah hi הודאת טביחה לאו הודאה היא, Hoda'at tevicha
lav hoda'ah hi, that the admission to the slaughtering is not an
admission because you didn't obligate yourself. What type of admission exempts you?
It's only an admission that at least forces you to pay the
principal. So that seems to be a good proof. Amri אמרי, Amri,
no, lo לא, lo, he, that doesn't prove it. We're not giving
the scenario of admitting to the Gneivah גניבה Gneivah to say the
halacha הלכה halacha wouldn't be the same if you admitted to the
tevicha טביחה. tevicha. Maybe it would be the same. Why are we
giving the scenario of admitting to the Gneivah גניבה? Gneivah? To tell
you a bigger Chiddush חידוש. Chiddush. היא גופא קא משמע לן *Hi
gufa kamashmalan*, it's telling you a חידוש *chiddush* about that case itself
of admitting to the גניבה gneiva. *gneva*. דכיון דאמר גנבתי ganavti *dekeivan
de'amar gnavti*, once you said you were... you did the גניבה gneiva.
*gneva*, אף על גב דאמר לא lo, טבחתי ולא מכרתי *af al
gav de'amar lo tavachti velo macharti*, even though you deny the טביחה
ומכירה tvicha u-mechira. *tvi'cha u'mechira*, so you would think you admitted to
the גניבה gneiva *gneva*, you denied טביחה ומכירה tvicha u-mechira. *tvi'cha u'mechira*,
then there are witnesses to טביחה ומכירה tveichah u'mechira. *tvi'cha u'mechira*, at
least pay the extra fine of the three and the five? No,
you don't have to. ובאו עדים edim שטבח ומכר פטור patur *uva'u
eidim shetavach umachar patur*, you remain exempt from the טביחה ומכירה tveichah
u'mechira *tvi'cha u'mechira* even though you denied it and you were lying.
Why? Why did you deny it and you were lying, why don't
you have to pay it? מאי טעמא Mai ta'ama? *mai ta'ama*, what's
the reason? תשלומי ארבעה וחמשה רחמנא *tashlumei arba'a vechamisha rachmana*, the Torah
said you pay four and five, ולא תשלומי ארבעה ולא תשלומי שלשה
*velo tashlumei arba'a velo tashlumei shlosha*, not four and three. Meaning the
reason it took out the four is because there's a problem, because
it says four and five, and if you admit you could still
be paying four, but I mean, it says you pay, you know,
five for the cow and not four for the cow, four for
the sheep and not three for the sheep. Okay, so therefore once
you've admitted to the... to the גניבה gneivah *gneva*, we take out
one of those payments, everything gets knocked down, right? One of those
units gets taken away and that's not what the Torah said. Okay,
so that's a big חידוש *chiddush* that you... I mean that's... that's
definitely פשט pshat *pshat*. The פשט *pshat* is: Look at this guy.
He only came to בית דין beis din *beis din* because he
saw the witnesses were about to testify. So it isn't really a
real testimony. And he continued to deny the טביחה ומכירה tveichah u'mechira
*tvi'cha u'mechira*, right? And he lied, he was lying about that because
we had witnesses that came about that and even so he gets
off of everything except the principal. So that's a big חידוש *chiddush*.
That's why we wanted to say that case. But maybe אי הכי
נמי *ei hachi nami*, maybe had he just admitted to the טביחה
ומכירה tevicha u'mechira, *tvi'cha u'mechira*, maybe that would exempt him as well.
So it's not really relevant to prove our question. You had a
question?
You mean the... you mean the טביחה tvicha ומכירה *tvi'cha u'mechira* isn't...
because if you didn't steal, then there's no problem טביחה tvicha ומכירה
*tvi'cha u'mechira*, give it to me, I don't even know what it
is.
Right, no, but the admission makes sense after there are עדי גניבה
gneiva *edei gneva*. That's why the admission makes sense.
No, but the other thing is like... but I'd still be a
פסול עד *pasul ed* going forward, right? Even if I don't pay
anything?
In this case?
Yeah, these guys? Yeah, sure.
Yeah, because you're a רשע דחמס *rasha d'chamas*, yeah, absolutely. I mean
because you're... because you were a גנב ganav. *gannav*, yeah. Okay, so
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: Okay, so that didn't prove it.
That was really just proving as גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says היא גופא
*hi gufa*, an extreme case where you could be such a weak
admission and still get off of pretty much every single except the
principal. Okay, so גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: לימא כתנאי *leima
ketana'ei*, let's say this debate question about an admission that does not
obligate you in the principal is ultimately a debate of תנאים *tana'im*.
Everybody agrees to Rav, an admission can exempt you, but is it
also true about an admission that doesn't obligate you in the principal?
Let's say this is a debate of
תנאים *tana'im*. Okay, היו שנים עדים eidim שגנב *hayu shnayim eidim sheganav*,
two people testified that you
were a גנב ganav *gannav*, והיו שנים עדים eidim, שטבח ומכר *vehayu
shnayim eidim shetavach umachar*, and two testified that you did the טביחה
ומכירה *tvi'cha u'mechira*, two others, right. הוזמו עדי גניבה geneivah *huzmu edei
gneva*, so the עדות eidus *eidut* that you were גנב ganav *gannav*
were proven to be זוממים zomemim *zomemim*, so עדות שבטלה מקצתה בטלה
כולה *eidut shebatla miktzata batla kula*. If you can't prove you were
גנב ganav, *gannav*, then obviously the טביחה ומכירה *tvi'cha u'mechira* is nothing,
maybe you were doing it to your own animal. Okay, so they
have to pay you כפל kefel. *kefel* and you pay nothing, even
though there's still עדים eidim *eidim* that you were טובח ומוכר toveach
u'mocher. *tove'ach u'mocher*, it doesn't mean anything now. עדות שבטלה מקצתה בטלה
כולה *eidut shebatla miktzata batla kula*. הוזמו עדי טביחה *huzmu edei tvi'cha*,
let's say the witnesses of the טביחה *tvi'cha* were proven זוממים *zomemim*,
הוא משלם תשלומי כפל tashlumei kefel. *hu meshalem tashlumei kefel* to the
owners because you're still a גנב ganav *gannav*, that part was still
true.
והן משלמים תשלומי שלשה *vehein meshalmim tashlumei shlosha*, and they pay you
three. So you were a גנב ganav, *gannav*, you have to pay
the owners, they were liars that you were טובח ומוכר *tove'ach u'mocher*,
or whether they were lying or not they were עדים זוממים edim
zomemim *eidim zomemim*, so they pay you the three.
What about what before, תשלומי כפל kefel *tashlumei kefel* and not תשלומי
ארבעה וחמשה *tashlumei arba'a vechamisha*?
Yeah, it's an interesting question. We don't say that by the עדים
זוממים edim zomemim. *eidim zomemim*. It's an interesting point. Okay, והן משלמים
תשלומי שלשה *vehein meshalmim tashlumei shlosha*. משום סומכוס Somchus אמרו *mishum Sumchus
amru*, in the name of סומכוס Somchus *Sumchus* they said,
הן משלמים תשלומי כפל meshalmim tashlumei khefel והוא משלם תשלומי שלשה ve-hu
meshalem tashlumei shlosha. *hein meshalmim tashlumei kefel vehu meshalem tashlumei shlosha*. No,
the עדים eidim *eidim* pay two and you pay three. What? What
sense does that make? You're a גנב ganav. *gannav*, they were liars
about the טביחה ומכירה *tvi'cha u'mechira*, he says they pay two and
you pay three? So that doesn't make any sense. Let's take a
look. I'm sorry, תשלומי שלשה לפר ושנים לאיל *tashlumei shlosha lapar ushnayim
la'ayil*. Okay, three for a cow and two for a ram. אהי
קאי סומכוס Somchus *ahi ka'ei Sumchus*, which case is סומכוס Sumchus *Sumchus*
going on? אילימא רישא *ileima reisha*,
now it certainly doesn't make sense at the end, right? Because the
end, as I said, is that you were a גנב ganav. *gannav*
and they were lying about the טביחה ומכירה *tvi'cha u'mechira*, it wouldn't
make sense for them to pay two and you pay three. The
case it could work, but it would also not make sense, but
at least you would understand how to begin thinking is that they
were proven זוממים *zomemim* on the גניבה gneiva *gneva*. Remember the first
case is they were זוממים *zomemim* on the גניבה gneiva? *gneva*, you
still have witnesses of טביחה ומכירה *tvi'cha u'mechira*. So סומכוס Sumchus *Sumchus*
would say, oh, they're זוממים *zomemim* on the גניבה gneiva. *gneva*, they
pay you כפל kefel? *kefel*. Oh, but there's still witnesses on the
טביחה ומכירה *tvi'cha u'mechira*, you pay the owner three. Now that doesn't
make sense because there's no witnesses that you're a גנב gannav, *gannav*,
but at least you could
begin... at least
you
could begin thinking. I understand, that's the problem, but at least anyway
that's the גמרא Gemara but that's the question. All right, exactly, at
least the two and the three match in that case. Okay.
אילימא רישא ליתא לסומכוס דפליג במקצת ופליג בכולא, Eileima reisha leisa le-Somchus
depalig bemiktzat upalig bekula, so that doesn't make sense, we get back
they pay two but how could you still be paying three once
there's no longer עדות about the
גניבה. gneiva אלא סיפא. Ella seifa. So it's the last case where
they're proven עדים זוממים edim zomemim. on the טביחה ומכירה. So really?
Why would they be paying two and you be paying three? שפיר
קאמרי רבנן. Shappir ka-amri rabanan. The Rabbis what they're saying is makes
you know is the only thing that makes sense in that case.
סומכוס משלם תשלומי כפל Somchus meshalem tashlumei khefel you pay the two
והם משלמים
תשלומי שלשה. ve-heim meshalmim tashlumei shlosha. So סומכוס Sumchus doesn't make any
sense. So because סומכוס Sumchus' doesn't make any sense, you gotta love
it when the גמרא Gemara says oh, let's say this is a
רביתא דתנאי ravita de-tana'ei or a ברייתא braita that doesn't make any
sense and then we'll explain it to fit our you know our
preconceived notions. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אלא ella here's how
the ברייתא braita makes sense. מילתא חריפתא בינייהו, Milta charifta beinyaihu, they
must be talking about some completely different case. We have to construct
a scenario
where סומכוס Sumchus could be saying that they pay two and you
pay three. So what could that scenario be? So must be the
following
case. כגון דאתו בי תרי אמרי ליה גנבת, Kegon d'asu bei trei
amri lei gnafta, two people say you're a גנב. gannav, אמר להון
Amar lehon you say to them אין גנבתי in gnafti fine I
admit I'm a גנב gannav, וטבחתי ומכרתי ve-tavachti u-macharti
and not only that I'll do you one better not only am
I a גנב gannav, I did טביחה ומכירה. מיהו Mihu however לא
בפניכם גנבתי. lo bifneichem gnafti. I didn't do it in front of
you, I saw who was around, so you're lying. Okay, maybe I
am a גנב, gannav, maybe I do owe the owner four and
five whatever okay but you're עדים זוממים. edim zomemim ואייתי סהדי דאזמינהו
דלא באנפיה גנב Ve-ayti sahadi de-azmineihu d'lo b'anpei ganav and then I
brought witnesses to prove that you could not have seen me do
the גניבה. geneivah You were somewhere else. You're the עדים זוממים. edim
zomemim. So now assuming I'm the גנב gannav, in this case, you
the עדים זוממים edim zomemim here, Michael and David, you're the עדים
זוממים. edim zomemim. You have to pay me now two. Whatever I
have to pay the owner I'll worry about. Fine I'm a גנב
טובח ומוכר ganav tove'ach u-mocher but you gotta pay me too. You
were lying. Okay.
Wait a minute I thought טבח ומכר tavach u-mchar part was what
we're lying about right?
No, all you said was
גנבת. gnafta. אייתי בי
תרי אמרי ליה גנבת. Aytei bei trei amri lei gnafta. Okay so
you're lying, you're going to have to pay me two. I might
have to pay the owner, I was a גנב טובח ומוכר ganav
tove'ach u-mocher although just now I did a הודאה hoda'ah so we'll
see about that but you start with you having to pay me
two. ואייתי בעל הבית סהדי Ve-ayti ba'al ha-bayit sahadi and then the
owner comes and he brings witnesses דאתו בי דינא וגנב וטבח ומכר
de-asu bei dina u-ganav u-tavach u-machar and he brings witnesses that I
did the whole shebang. So you have to pay me two. Do
I have to pay anything to the owner? Now let's think about
it. What I did was I admitted. Now I admitted because maybe
you came to court so that has to be like the מודה
בקנס פטור modeh be-k'nas patur case. Although at the end of the
day did you really, was you know since you're lying do we
really see that my admission is weakened because I responded to you
because in the end of the day you were lying? Okay so
anyway but let's assume for now it was a real admission. You
pay me two. I did an admission so if I did an
admission I shouldn't have to pay the owner anything. I mean I
pay him the קרן keren the principal nothing else right? 'Cause I
said גנבתי וטבחתי ומכרתי gnafti ve-tavachti u-macharti I said all of that.
Okay so now what's going to be my obligation to the owner?
דאתו בי דינא וגנב וטבח ומכר. De-asu bei dina u-ganav u-tavach u-machar.
ובהדא דטביחה קמיפלגי U-vahada de-tvicha kamiflagi the debate is whether my admission
to the טביחה is an admission right? דרבנן סברי אף על גב
דהודאת גניבה מחמת עדים הוא דקא מודי De-rabanan savri af al gav
de-hoda'at gneiva machmat edim hu de-ka modei even though when I admitted
to the גניבה geneivah I was reacting to you even though you
turned out to be עדים זוממים edim zomemim I didn't know I
would be able to truly prove you as עדים זוממים. edim zomemim.
That was a reacting to you. Nevertheless הודאה דטביחה הודאה היא hoda'ah
de-tvicha hoda'ah hi it still counts like מודה בקנס פטור. modeh be-k'nas
patur.
So therefore if that was a good admission that I did to
the owner even though you were coming I admitted I did the
whole thing I only have to pay the קרן keren right? Everybody
with me? 'Cause you came I admitted to the whole thing I
proved you to be זוממים I admitted I'm only going to have
to pay the owner the קרן keren and פטור patur. and I'm
totally off the hook for everything. Wait what? Why because מודה בקנס?
modeh be-k'nas? Yeah מודה בקנס פטור modeh be-k'nas patur right.
וסומכוס סבר Ve-Somchus savar no כיון דהודאת גניבה מחמת עדים הוא דקא
מודי keivan de-hoda'at gneiva machmat edim hu de-ka modei I'm only being
מודה modeh because you showed up in
court okay where was I?
וסומכוס סבר כיון דהודאת גניבה מחמת עדים הוא דקא
מודי הודאה דטביחה לאו הודאה היא
Ve-Somchus savar keivan de-hoda'at gneiva machmat edim hu de-ka modei
hoda'ah
de-tvicha lav hoda'ah hi right okay so therefore since I'm doing it
in responding to you right my admission to the טביחה is not
an admission. Okay so therefore I'm not going to get off the
hook. והנך עדים קאזמינהו. Ve-hanach edim ka-azmineihu.
So these original עדים eidim? משלמים תשלומי כפל kefel you pay me
two והוא משלם תשלומי שלשה. Since I'm liable I'm going to pay
the owner. So my admission was not admission to get me off
the hook. So I'm still going to pay if he brings other
עדים edim to prove that I did the whole thing, I'm still
going to pay the three or so on to the owner. Okay,
now the question here is one minute, hold on, I just gotta
think this through, because then why don't I pay
Oh, no, here's the point. I really have to pay everything to
the owner, right, this is what רש״י Rashi says, okay, you are
lying, you pay me כפל. kefel סומכוס Sumchus says my admission to
the owner is not an admission. It was all done because you
were here, that that sort of motivated me to admit that's nothing.
The owner brings עדים, I have to pay the owner everything. So
I owe the owner now four and five. How are we going
to pay off this four and five? Well, two are going to
come from you. You're going to pay me and I'm going to
pay him, and then I'm going to pay the balance myself. Okay,
so I really owe the owner the full four five, but think
what סומכוס Sumchus is saying: you pay two of it, since you're
זוממין, zommin, you're going to pay me and I'm going to hand
it back to and I'm going to hand it to him, and
I'm going to pay the balance yeah, the three is the balance.
Yeah, because the עדים have proven that I'm a גנב, gannav, and
now it's really the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to say it's actually one
less wait one second because my admission to the קרן keren clearly
obligates me, my הודאה hoda'ah doesn't exempt me because it was in
reacting to you guys, okay, and therefore I owe the owner the
full amount. He's proven עדים that I'm a גנב וטבח ומכר. ganav
v'tovach u'machar. So two of it's come from you and the other
three come from me.
And רבנן Rabbanan say since we were
זוממין, zommin, and the רבנן Rabbanan say my admission is still a
good admission.
So your הודאה hoda'ah My הודאה hoda'ah
is still a good admission, right, exactly.
So he only accounts for three, right? Three plus two, it's not
a balance for the two plus two, that goes to be what
do you mean?
If there was a case of five, it was a balance of
three. If it was a case of four, it's a balance of
two, depending on if it's an ox or a sheep. All right,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so that's the issue.
סומכוס Sumchus over here וסומכוס סבר כיוון משום דשכיח פר ושניים איל.
v'Sumchus savar keivan mishum d'shachach par v'shnayim ayil.
Okay. אמר רב אחא בריה דרב איקא, Amar Rav Acha brei d'Rav
Ika, so therefore anyway what do you see?
So that now how does that prove this issue? That really proves
the issue of עדים המכחישין בו, eidim hamachshishin bo, that's really not
the case
about ברייתא, braisa, that's how it's sort of framed the debate. One
minute, one minute. Wasn't the
מחלוקת machlokes
whether הודאה דטביחה hoda'ah d'tveichah is הודאה? hoda'ah? Yeah, but then but
why does it say because of the עדים? סומכוס סבר כיוון דהודאה
דגניבה מכוח עדים הוא דקא מודה. Sumchus savar keivan d'hoda'ah d'gneivah mikoach
eidim hu d'ka modeh. הודאה דגניבה. hoda'ah d'gneivah. Oh,
that's the point, right, thank you. So סומכוס' Sumchus point is the
following, meaning thank you, thank you, I missed that explanation. Okay, so
the רבנן Rabbanan say my הודאה hoda'ah is totally good. My הודאה
hoda'ah was a double הודאה, hoda'ah, thank you. It was a הודאה
hoda'ah of גניבה geneivah plus הודאה hoda'ah of the טביחה ומכירה. So
the רבנן Rabbanan say even though you were present, it was
considered a good הודאה hoda'ah and it's a הודאה hoda'ah that incorporates
two things. I admit to the קרן, keren, right, and I admit
to the גניבה טביחה ומכירה. gneivah tveichah u'mechira. But since I'm admitting
but therefore I'm getting off of the whole thing and therefore I'm
פטור. pattur, Okay, whereas סומכוס Sumchus says no one minute, you didn't
really admit to the קרן keren meaning in this case you said
גנב. ganav, I said גנבתי וטבחתי ומכרתי. ganavti v'tavachti u'macharti. So my
admission to טביחה ומכירה was not because of you. You're only saying
גנב. ganav, My admission of טביחה ומכירה was totally sincere. Okay, but
סומכוס Sumchus, says but that's the admission סומכוס Sumchus says the admission
of
גנבתי ganavti, is not a real admission because I was responding to
you guys. So therefore that doesn't count as a הודאה. hoda'ah. Okay,
so therefore there's no admission to the קרן. keren. I'm only doing
it because you guys are here. The only thing I'm really מודה
modeh to that I'm not being done because I'm feeling compelled to
admit to is טובח ומוכר. So סומכוס Sumchus says but that doesn't
get you off the hook because that's an admission that does not
come with obligating yourself
in
a
קרן. keren. Okay, so there you see that סומכוס Sumkhos, holds that
the second part of the admission, since it doesn't come with any
obligation, still gets you off the hook.
Okay, so that's where at least you see what סומכוס holds.
The clarity of an admission is based upon the fact that there
could be consequences.
Right, I mean if you want to base it on sincerity, maybe
it's just the formal definition that an admission has to mean consequences,
again whether it's the question about what. motivating him or the practical
reality that it's obligating him, but one way or the other, שמואל
Shmuel says the reason you are still going to have to pay
the owner the full amount, but I admitted to the תביעה דכסא,
tvia dechisa, they weren't saying anything about it, let that get me
off the hook. No, since that didn't come with any obligation, it
doesn't get you off the hook.
Just small question, it's not really with the context. Right, the דתניא
de tanya is not redundant?
No, no, that was the end of the discussion yesterday. Yesterday said
we can prove it from a משנה Mishnah and prove it from
a ברייתא. brayta. Here we're going to now prove it from the
ברייתא, brayta, דתניא. de tanya.
No, I know, but it was explicating a statement yesterday. Yesterday it
just said we could prove it from a משנה, Mishnah, prove it
from a ברייתא. brayta. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says, okay. So
look, by reconstructing this case to give a scenario where שמואל Shmuel
says, they pay two and I pay three, סומכוס, I did it
again. They pay two and I pay three, the only way that
makes sense is this scenario we've just now constructed and therefore it's
a case where סומכוס is implicitly saying that an admission to just
תביעה דכסא tvia dechisa is not a real admission. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר
רב אחא בריה דרב איקא, Amar Rav Acha brei deRav Ika, לא,
no, that's not the only way to reconstruct this. דכולי עלמא הודאת
תביעה לאו הודאה היא. Dechulei alma hoda'at tvia la'av hoda'ah hi. Everybody
could agree to what we're saying in רב, Rav, that if you
just that your admission to the תביעה tvia by itself does not
obligate you because there's no real consequence to it. אלא בעדות שאי
אתה יכול להזימה קמיפלגי. Ella be'edut she'atah yachol lehazimuh kamiflegi. So what's
the debate about? A testimony that cannot ultimately be proven into זוממין.
zomemin. What's that scenario? כגון דאתו סהדי ואמרי ליה, Kegon de'atu sahadi
ve'amri leh, גנבת, ganavta, you stole. ואמר להו גנבתי וטבחתי ומכרתי. Ve'amar
lehu ganavti vetavachti umacharti.
Same
way we set up here. David and Michael told me I'm a
גנב, ganav I said yes, I'm a גנב, ganav וטבח וטבח ומכרתי,
vetovach vetovach umacharti, although you'd better מי לא בפניכם גנבתי mi lo
bifneichem ganavti and the same type of thing. It wasn't you guys,
אלא בפני פלוני ופלוני. ella bifnei ploni uploni. And it was in
front of ראובן ושמעון Reuven and Shimon that I did it. ואתו
סהדי ואזימנהו דלא באפיך גנב Ve'atu sahadi ve'azminu de'lo be'apaikh ganav
and then witnesses came and proved that you were עדים זוממים edim
zomemim, and I stole but it wasn't in your presence, so you're
going to have to pay me two. ואתו פלוני ופלוני ואשרו ביה
דגנב וטבח ומכר. Ve'atu ploni uploni ve'ashru beih deganav vetavach vemachar. And
then ראובן ושמעון Reuven and Shimon who I said, if you want
witnesses to come and prove that I was a גנב, ganav you
should be bringing ראובן ושמעון. Reuven and Shimon. They saw me doing
it. So the בעל הבית ba'al habayit said great idea. So he
went and he brought ראובן ושמעון. Reuven and Shimon. Okay. ואשרו ביה
דגנב וטבח ומכר. Ve'ashru beih deganav vetavach vemachar. ובהא Ubeha
now remember, although I said טבחתי מכרתי, tavachti macharti, that's not an
admission because that didn't obligate myself for anything. And presumably, although I
admitted גנבתי, presumably that's also not an admission because that's because you
were present. So everybody should be saying now, so everybody agrees you
pay כפל kefel. because you guys are עדים זוממים. edim zomemim Presumably,
though, everybody should be saying that I should pay the בעל הבית
ba'al habayit everything because ראובן ושמעון Reuven and Shimon came and said
I have to owe and my admissions didn't count as admissions. So
what's the debate? ובהא קמיפלגי, Ubeha kamiflegi, this is the debate. רבנן
סברי, Rabbanan savri, הוי ליה עדות שאי אתה יכול להזימה havi leh
edut she'atah yachol lehazimuh ועדות שאי אתה יכול להזימה לא הויא עדות.
ve'edut she'atah yachol lehazimuh lo havya edut.
Very strange idea. You know why when ראובן ושמעון Reuven and Shimon
came I don't have to pay based on their testimony? Because since
I said they saw me, I am basically like supporting the testimony
against me. Now the normal principle is that if you have testimony
that could never be proven זוממין, zomemin, then it's not good. Presumably
because
it's that they're not afraid of lying if they can never be
proven זוממין. zomemin. An example that they can never be proven זוממין
zomemin is they say what day did it happen, I'm not sure.
You know what time, I'm not sure. So they give themselves an
escape clause, you can never nail them down, right, you never prove
that they're lying and prove them עדים זוממים, edim zomemim right, so
therefore you can't trust the testimony. Somehow it's the threat of the
consequences of being found עדים זוממים edim zomemim, that allows us to
be able to accept this testimony as trustworthy. Okay, so that's the
normal principle that עדות שאי אתה יכול להזימה, edut she'ey atah yachol
lehazimah, if you can't prove they're זוממין, zomemin, then it's not good.
Here the irony is, the גמרא Gemara says you know why you
can't prove they're זוממין? zomemin? Because you're so certain that it's true.
Okay. Since I said they saw me and I the accused
am supporting their testimony, then that makes it like protected testimony. I
understand, that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to answer. It's a strange
idea that that makes it עדות שאי אתה יכול להזימה edut she'ey
atah yachol lehazimah and therefore because it's sort of like when a
בית דין all says חייב, chayav, you have to throw it out.
It's too fishy or whatever. So here there's no, if I'm supporting
their testimony, I'm the one who said they saw me, that can't.
So let's just read it one minute. ועדות שאי אתה יכול להזימה
לא הויא עדות. ve'edut she'ey atah yachol lehazimah lo havya edut. So
therefore I'm off the hook. You pay me two and I'm off
the hook. So I mean by the way also somebody who's really
smart then. The same way to be really smart you would admit
to a קנס k'nas and prevent yourself from ever paying. If you're
really smart you would always say hey go bring those עדים against
me. וסומכוס סבר VeSumchus savar עדות שאי אתה יכול להזימה הויא עדות,
edut she'ey atah yachol lehazimah havya edut, it still counts. And therefore
I am חייב chayav four and five. Since I'm חייב chayav four
and five, you guys pay two of it and I pay the
remaining three. So the גמרא Gemara says how could that be the
debate? וקיימא לן Ve'kayma lan עדות שאי אתה יכול להזימה לא הויא
עדות, edut she'ey atah yachol lehazimah lo havya edut, everybody says it's
no good. So no, how could סומכוס say I do have to
pay? No.
הני מילי היכא דלא ידע
באיזה...
Hani mili
heicha delo yada be'ei zeh...
It has to be more precise, otherwise it's עדות שאי אתה יכול
להזימה. edut she'e'ata yakhol lehazima.
So you were with me on vacation in New Jersey?
It's possible, but it makes it a lot harder.
But actually, the position of the חכמים Chachamim strength. Anyway, here's a
case where the גמרא Gemara, tries to make it a מחלוקת תנאים
machloket tanna'im because you had a bizarre idea of סומכוס, so we
had to construct a whole scenario around it. Anytime you have to
construct a scenario, it's going to be obviously very hard to be
a proof for anything, because you could always imagine a different scenario.
Yes.
Why doesn't the principle of אין אדם משים עצמו רשע ein adam
mesim atzmo rasha apply here?
You're admitting you're a...
what do you mean?
In terms
of חייב khayav in the קרן? keren? אין אדם משים עצמו רשע
ein adam mesim atzmo rasha just means that your own
admission, first of all, it's different than the United States, the pleading
the fifth. Fifth means you can't be forced to testify against yourself.
Here, it means if you testify against yourself, you cannot be found
guilty based on the weight of your own testimony. But if you're
going to tell us something that's going to point us to witnesses,
and you're going to be found guilty based on witnesses, you can
be found guilty. And even that, by the way, is only in
terms of something like קנס. knas. In terms of a ממון mamon
payment, a compensatory payment, you are obligated based on your own admission.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Let's just wrap this
up.
אמר מר, Amar Mar, they pay תשלומי כפל. kefel, You pay me
two and I pay the remaining three and four based on, in
this scenario. מכדי קא מודה דגנב, mikhdi ka modeh degannav, one minute,
wait, whatever scenario you just constructed, I'm admitting I was the גנב,
right? So in that case, if I'm admitting that I was a
גנב, why are Michael and David paying me כפל? kefel. They were
lying, they might have been lying about
that I was
a whatever-you-call-it, that they didn't see me גנב בפניהם, ganav bifneihem, and
they're coming to be מחייב mechayev me a כפל kefel that I'm
not really obligated based on their testimony. But if it turns out
that I actually was a גנב, then
the principal they were trying to make me pay I really owed.
So it's interesting, even though they were sort of lying about the
facts because they weren't there, but they weren't trying to make me
pay something I was innocent of, and therefore they shouldn't have to
pay me the
principal.
Okay, so you should
have to pay me the one, not two, both units, but the
one of the two units I actually was obligated in, even maybe
you didn't see it and you were lying about what you said,
but you weren't trying to make me pay something I didn't owe.
Okay. מכדי קא מודה דגנב קרן בשלומי, mikhdi ka modeh degannav keren
bishlumai, so I have to pay the קרן. keren. So אמר רב
אלעזר משמיה דרבי תני, Amar Rav Elazar mishmei de'Rabbi Tani, משמיה דרבי,
mishmei de'Rabbi, משמיה דרב, mishmei de'Rav, excuse me, תני תשלומי כפל. tani
tashlumei kefel.
When it says כפל kefel. it doesn't mean two units, it means
one unit, the extra payment because of the כפל. kefel You pay
the fine part of it, I pay the principal, you pay the
fine. So when it says you pay me the כפל, it really
means you pay the balance of the כפל. Okay, moving on, that
was once again עדים זוממים and now we can hopefully move on
from that. We're always going to be revisiting עדים זוממים, but that
was the end of this question of, again, three opinions whether your
admission obligates you. Everybody agrees your admission doesn't obligate you. שמואל Shmuel
says, רב Rav says it goes further, it exempts you. And then
within רב Rav there's two variations, either it always exempts you or
only exempts you if it came with an obligation that actually forced
you to pay something. If it forced you to pay something, then
it exempts you from additional payment. Okay, now we move on in
the משנה. Mishna. גנב והקדיש ואחר כך טבח ומכר. gannav ve'hikdish ve'achar
kach tovach u'machar.
You did גניבה and then you sanctified it, and then you slaughtered
it. So when you slaughter or sold it after you sanctified it,
you're not going to pay because you don't pay these things for
הקדש, hekdesh, there's a general exemption for הקדש. hekdesh. Another way of
saying it is it no longer belongs to the owner, it belongs
to הקדש. hekdesh. So when you're slaughtering or selling it, you're slaughtering
or selling something that doesn't belong to the owner. But the גמרא
Gemara has a question. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. אמרי,
Amri, says the גמרא, Gemara בשלמא טביחה לא מחייב, bishlama tevicha lo
mechayev, I get when you slaughter it after you were מקדיש makdish
it, you're not going to pay for that, דכי טבח דהקדש טבח,
de'ki tavakh de'hekdesh tavakh, you're slaughtering something that belongs to הקדש, hekdesh,
ולא דמראי טבח, velo de'marei tavakh, it no longer belongs to the
owner. אלא ההקדש לחייב, ella ha'hekdesh lekhayyev, but for הקדש hekdesh do
pay for the act of being מקדיש makdish it! I get after
you're מקדיש makdish it you're not going to pay for טביחה ומכירה,
but why is the act of being מקדיש makdish it not like
selling it to someone? You gave it over to הקדש. hekdesh. מה
לי מכר להדיוט מה לי מכר לשמים? ma li machar le'hediyot ma
li machar lishmayim? What do I care if you sold it to
ראובן, Reuven, what do I care if you sold it to the
בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash? You took this animal that you stole and
you sanctified it, you transferred it away from the owner to the
ownership of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Good question. So the גמרא
Gemara says, הא מני רבי שמעון היא, ha manni Rebbe Shimon hi,
it's רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon who said דאמר קדשים שחייב באחריותן ברשותיה
דמרא קיימי. de'amar kodshim she'khayav be'achrayutan birshutei de'marei kamei. No, it's רבי
שמעון Rebbe Shimon who said
that קדשים kodshim that you are obligated in their liability are still
considered to not have left your control, but to be considered to
be under your control. What does that mean? It means if I,
let's say, have to bring a חטאת chatat and I sanctify this
animal, this animal What does that mean? It means if I let's
say have to bring a חטאת chatas and I sanctify this animal,
this animal what happens if it gets lost? I have to bring
another one because I'm obligated in a חטאת. chatas. Or if I
say הרי עלי עולה, Harei alai olah, right? So I obligate myself
for an עולה. olah. So if this animal that I sanctified gets
lost, I'll have to make a give a substitute, another one. So
that case where I'm going to lose out if I lose this
animal, it's still considered under my control, not under הקדש hekdesh's control.
Okay, it's sort of like דבר הגורם לממון כממון דמי, davar hagorem
lemamon kemamon dami, if you sort of remember that idea, right? Since
its loss will cause me a loss, it's like I still own
it and it's still under my possession. All right, so therefore רבי
שמעון Rebbe Shimon imagines the case: I stole here from David, but
you know, I might be a גנב, but I'm still פרום, frum,
so I have to bring a חטאת chatas for some other sin
I did. So I'm going to sanctify this animal as a חטאת.
chatas. And that's not considered like a מכירה, mechira, because since I
would be have to replace it if I lost it, it's still
under my control and it's not like I sold it to some
third party yet. That would be the way why the sanctifying would
not be considered yet like a selling, because since I am liable
for it, it's like it's still under my control. Okay, what?
Can you do a מצוה mitzvah with the stolen?
No, then it's true, then it's like, you know, it's מצוה הבאה
בעבירה mitzvah haba'ah ba'aveirah and קרבנו ולא גזלו korbano velo gezelo and
all those types of things. Right. But that's not the issue right
now. If I טיבחה tivcha afterwards, I'm exempt because then it might
not be mine, it might not, it's right. רש"י Rashi points this
out. It's a little bit ironic, meaning I didn't sell it enough
away to take it away from me to make me חייב chayav
for מכירה. mechira. But because it no longer belongs to the owner
because it's הקדש, hekdesh, I'm also not חייב chayav when I then
slaughter it afterwards. Right? It's this interesting middle space, right? מכירה mechira
both takes it further away from the owner and takes it away
from my possession. Sanctifying it, if I'm חייב אחריותו, chayav achrayusto, means
that it's not it's not away from my possession, it's still under
my control, but it is further away from the owner's possession because
now it belongs to הקדש. hekdesh. So it's like an interesting way
in which I'm not חייב chayav for sanctifying it, but I'm exempt
if I slaughter it afterwards. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says:
We're on...
so that's the answer. דחייב באחריותו וברשותא דמריה קאי. dechayav beachrayuto uvrashuta
demarei kaei. גמרא Gemara says: One minute. הני בסבר רבי שמעון, hani
besever Rebbe Shimon,
since the end of the משנה Mishnah is רבי שמעון, Rebbe Shimon,
we'll get to the end of the משנה, Mishnah, but רבי שמעון
Rebbe Shimon is quoted at the end of our משנה Mishnah הוי.
havei. רישא לאו רבי שמעון. reisha lav Rebbe Shimon.
Presumably this first opinion can't be assuming רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon because
this first... the next line after this position is the opinion of
רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon quoted in the משנה. Mishnah. אלא, Ella, although
that was a great answer. אלא הכא במאי עסקינן, Ella hacha bemai
askinan, what are we talking about? בקדשים קלים ואליבא דרבי יוסי הגלילי.
bekodshim kalim vealiba deRebbe Yose HaGlili. Okay, fine. Another way in which
it's still considered the owner's. It is according to רבי יוסי הגלילי
Rebbe Yose HaGlili when you sanctify something not as a חטאת chatas
or an עולה, olah, but as a שלמים. shelamim. By שלמים shelamim
you get to eat the meat. So since you're going to be
able to eat the meat, it's still considered yours and under your
control and still considered, right? So it's a different way in which
it's considered yours. So again it would be this interesting middle space
where because it's still mine,
I haven't done a מכירה, mechira, but because I've removed it further
from the owner, I'm not חייב chayav now if I slaughter it
afterwards. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says: אבל קדשי קדשים מאי? aval
kodshei kodshim mai? So the גמרא Gemara says: אבל קדשי קדשים מאי?
aval kodshei kodshim mai?
So what would you say though if it was holy of holies?
That it was something that you couldn't eat the meat? Then תשלם
תשלומי ארבע וחמשה? tishalem tashlumei arba vechamishah?
Then you'd say you would pay four and five? Because then that
would be like a מכירה mechira because you took it away from
yourself as well when you sanctified it. One minute. אדתני רישא, adetani
reisha, the beginning of the משנה Mishnah says: גנב וטבח ואחר כך
הקדיש, ganav vetavach veacharkach hikdish, משלם תשלומי ארבע וחמשה. meshallem tashlumei arba
vechamishah. If you stole it and you sold and slaughtered and then
you sanctified, then you pay four and five. It sounds like that
the only time you pay four and five is if you did
this before הקדש. hekdesh. That there'll be no scenario of הקדש hekdesh
that you'd be obligated in. So according to you,
לפלוג ולתני בדידי, liflog uletni bdidi, why don't you make a distinction
within the case of הקדש hekdesh itself that sometimes the act of
הקדש hekdesh according to you you would have to pay? במה דברים
אמורים, bamei devarim amurim,
when is it that when you're מקדיש makdish it you don't have
to pay? If you're מקדיש makdish it before the slaughtering or the
selling? בקדשים קלים, bekodshim kalim, when it's these lighter sacrifices that they're
still considered yours. אבל בקדשי קדשים, aval bekodshei kodshim, but if you
gave... made them the holy sacrifices, the holiest, then משלם תשלומי ארבע
וחמשה, meshallem tashlumei arba vechamishah, you would have to pay because the
act of הקדש hekdesh is like an act of sale, which the
גמרא Gemara could have said a minute ago too with רבי שמעון.
Rebbe Shimon. So what the גמרא'ס Gemara's basically saying is: Look, the
simple sense of the משנה Mishnah is there's no scenario of הקדש
hekdesh that you'd have to pay. The act of הקדש hekdesh does
not make you pay. Why not? There's got to be some case
where either it's קדשי קדשים kodshei kodshim or not חייב אחריותו chayav
achrayuto where the act of הקדש hekdesh kicks it out of your
control, out of the owner's control, out of your control, gives it
full over to הקדש. hekdesh. Let that be like a מכירה. mechira.
But the משנה Mishnah doesn't sound like it. The משנה Mishnah sounds
like the act of הקדש hekdesh is never a מכירה. mechira. How
do you explain that? So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
ולא שנא קדשי קדשים ולא שנא קדשים קלים. velo shena kodshei kodshim
velo shena kodshim kalim. Okay. גמרא Gemara's says like, I'm sorry, מאי?
mai? Did I skip a line? תשלומי ארבע וחמשה. tashlumei arba vechamishah.
אלא לעולם, Ella le'olam, fine, you're right. לא שנו קדשי קדשים ולא
שנו קדשים קלים. lo shanu kodshei kodashim velo shanu kodashim kalim. It
doesn't matter what type of הקדש. hekdesh. The משנה, mishna, you're right,
makes it clear that by הקדש hekdesh you never have to pay.
It's never considered an act of מכירה. mechira. So דקשיא לך, deka'shya
lach, you were wondering, מה לי מכר להדיוט מה לי מכר לשמים?
mah li machar lahedyot mah li machar lashamayim? What do I care
who you sold it to? You sold it to the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, you still sold it. So why therefore should you not
have to pay? So no, here's the difference. מה
לי מכר להדיוט מה לי מכר לשמים. mah li machar lahedyot mah
li machar lashamayim. מכר להדיוט, machar lahedyot, מעיקרא תורא דראובן והשתא תורא
דשמעון. me'ikara tora deReuven vehashta tora deShimon. When you sold it, I'm
sorry, והשתא תורא דשמעון. vehashta tora deShimon. If I sold it to
a normal guy, it used to be mine, or the owner, or
whatever, looked like mine, and now I sold it to שמעון, Shimon,
now it's his. That's what happens when you sell. It's no longer
associated with you. Okay,
but מכר לשמים, machar lashamayim, when you sanctify it, מעיקרא תורא דראובן
והשתא תורא דראובן. me'ikara tora deReuven vehashta tora deReuven. If I steal
this animal and I'm מקדיש makdish it as a חטאת chatas or
an עולה, olah, what do we say about this animal? We say,
oh look, there's the בית המקדש's Beis Hamikdash עולה? olah? No, we
say there's דב's Dov עולה, olah, right? So it might be sanctified,
but my name is still associated with it. So it's like saying,
you know, the whole point before about קדשים קלים ממון בעלים kodashim
kalim mamon be'alim or you know, or קדשים שחייב באחריותן kodashim shechayav
be'achrayutan is like it's still in your control. That's like a real
formal sense like you're still the owner. Even if you're not really
the owner, it's קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim and all of those things,
it still is associated with you. The idea of a קרבן korban
is it's still your קרבן. korban. And therefore, from the perspective of,
if we were to say are you the owner, the answer would
be no. Right, at most we say you're considered the owner maybe
if it's קדשים קלים kodashim kalim according to רבי יוסי הגלילי. Rabbi
Yossi HaGlili. Or it's חייב באחריותן chayav be'achrayutan according to רבי שמעון.
Rabbi Shimon. You're not the owner. Okay, but it still is associated
with you and therefore that's not enough to be חייב chayav for
מכירה. mechira. When the תורה Torah says that you slaughter it and
you sell it, in that case you pay four and five, that's
gotta be a classic מכירה mechira that after you sell it, it's
no longer associated with you. Here even after you sanctify it, it's
still seen as your קרבן. korban. Now one minute.
This points to two very different types of הקדש. hekdesh. Because תוספות
Tosafot says, if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says, והשתא
תורא דשמעון, vehashta tora deShimon, says תוספות, Tosafot, ובהא דאמר לקמן, veha
de'amar le'kaman, we say later, גנב והקדיש חייב
ארבעה וחמישה. ganav vehikdish chayav arba'ah vechamishah. There's actually explicitly the act
of הקדש hekdesh as an act of selling. תוספות Tosafot says, והוי
כמכר להדיוט, vehavai kemachar lahedyot, just like selling to a normal person,
היינו בקדשי בדק הבית. hainu bekodshei bedek habayis.
That's when you give it as a donation to the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. דלא מיקרו על שם בעלים. delo mikru al shem be'alim.
Okay, that it's not called after your name. Now what does that
mean? It means that, well, it both means, I mean, think about
it. If I go ahead and I donate my car to the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, right, do people say oh that's דב's Dov
holy car, sanctified car? No. They might say it's the car that
דב Dov donated. But at the end of the day, it's the
בית המקדש's Beis Hamikdash car, right? If I sanctify the sheep as
a קרבן, korban, then they'll say it's דב's Dov עולה, olah, that
he has to now bring to the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. They
won't say it's the בית המקדש's Beis Hamikdash עולה, olah, they'll say
it's my עולה. olah. Okay, if I gave my sheep as a
donation, they'll say oh look at this nice donation that we got
from דב, Dov, but they're not gonna say it's דב's Dov sheep,
now it's our sheep, he gave it to us, right? So therefore
the association with it is only in the case of a קרבן,
korban, not in the case of a קדשי בדק הבית. kodshei bedek
habayis. And the logic by the way, and it's interesting because the
גמרא Gemara, here is focusing on the end result, but it could
also have focused on the process. And the process is very different
and why this case is not a מכירה. mechira. What's the process
when I donate my sheep to the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? Basically,
if דוד Dovid there is the גזבר, gizbar, is the treasurer of
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, the process of donating my sheep is:
here, take my sheep, this is my gift to the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. That's just like a process of מכירה. mechira. He basically
is some legal entity that owns property, right? Like, who isn't like
the biggest landowner in Italy? Like the church or whatever, right? Or
as they, anyway, so he's some legal entity, maybe the biggest landowner
in the world, anyway, anyway, he's some legal entity that owns property
that owns property that owns property, and I'm giving this piece of
property and they take possession of it. That's מכירה. mechira. That I
would be חייב. chayav. But if this here little sheep, my white
little sheep here, if this little sheep I say: Zap! I'm sanctifying
you as an עולה. olah. That's not a process of giving something
over to some other entity to own it. That's a process of
instilling it with קדושה kedusha to serve a purpose that it can
now function as a קרבן korban that I can now bring it
as a קרבן. korban. That's about changing its status, not about changing
its ownership. Instilling it with קדושה. kedusha. So the same way the
גמרא Gemara says, oh before it's now it's also my עולה, olah,
you could just say it's not a real מכירה mechira because it's
still associated with me. But there's a more profound point. It's not
a real מכירה mechira because a מכירה mechira is about transferring ownership
and sanctifying something as a קרבן korban is not about transferring ownership,
it's about giving
it
קדושה. kedusha.
I think that there's a theological implication in the way you've distinguished
between status as opposed to ownership. That is to say if I'm
מקדיש makdish an animal as an עולה, olah, right? So clearly if
I use it there's an issue of מעילה me'ilah that has to
be—right—so there's a type of partnership that's implicit in being מקדיש makdish
an animal as a קרבן. korban.
Yeah, well I think that the question—so you are right, meaning the
questions of מעילה me'ilah are—the whole question of the מעילה, me'ilah, of
misuse, is: Do you conceptualize מעילה me'ilah as a type of גניבה
or גזילה gezeilah of taking possession of something that isn't yours? Or
do you conceptualize it as an איסור הנאה? issur hana'ah? This thing
is sanctified so cannot therefore be
misused—not taken away, but misused—for a secular non-sanctified purposes, right? So those
are the two different ways of conceptualizing מעילה. me'ilah. And what you
say is absolute—absolutely correct, that it might reflect two different types of
sanctity. A sanctity of בדק הבית bedek habayit might be much more
about a type of stealing, I'm taking it away because it's theirs
and I'm making it mine, whereas a sanctity of קרבנות korbanot might
much more be a lot more about misuse than about taking possession
of. So yes, what you're saying is absolutely—if I understood you
correctly, those two ways of thinking about מעילה me'ilah reflect what we
are now describing as two different concepts of קדושה, kedusha, what it's
about. Is it about ownership? Is it about status? Okay, yeah.
It sounds like what's at stake also is שינוי השם shinui hashem
never happened.
Well, תוספות Tosafot says if a שינוי השם shinui hashem never happened,
then תוספות Tosafot says that it wouldn't, you know, then the conversation
wouldn't have got off the ground. It wouldn't just be a השתא
דמעיקרא והשתא דרובא, hashta d'me'ikara v'hashta d'rubba, it would have been like
you didn't do anything. So if you look at the continuation of
תוספות, Tosafot, he says—he says no, a שינוי shinui definitely did happen.
He says—he says וקדשי מזבח חמורי דאף על גב דמעיקרא שם בהמה
v'kadshei mizbei'ach chamuri d'af al gav d'me'ikara shem behema it says not
only is there a שינוי השם shinui hashem because now it's called
a קרבן, korban, he says ולא הוי הקדש כמכירה מכל מקום למאן
דאמר יש לו קנין חשוב כשינוי רשות והכא איכא למימר דחל הקדש
אחר יאוש. v'lo havai hekdesh k'mechira mikol makom l'man d'amar yeish lo
kinyan chashuv k'shinui reshut v'hacha eika l'meimar d'chal hekdesh achar ye'ush. So
he says if you look at the earlier סוגיא, sugya, even before
the גמרא Gemara there introduced the idea of שינוי השם, shinui hashem,
it's—it's understood that הקדש hekdesh would work because it would be like
a שינוי רשות. shinui reshut. So it is not—it's not as all
or nothing as I just described. Right? Once something does become a
קרבן, korban, it is considered under the auspices of הקדש. hekdesh. It's
not just totally mine with its קדושה, kedusha, right? So that's what
תוספות Tosafot does say. So I oversimplified it, it's true.
It's the קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf versus שינוי רשות.
shinui reshut. No, certainly שינוי השם. shinui hashem. His whole point is
that even you don't—שינוי השם shinui hashem is the easy thing to
say. Once I say מעיקרא תורא דראובן והשתא תורא דראובן, me'ikara tora
d'Reuven v'hashta tora d'Reuven, I don't—they say okay, maybe I'll call it
שינוי השם shinui hashem because I'll call it a קרבן, korban, but
I'm not going to call it a שינוי רשות shinui reshut because
it's still under my control. And תוספות Tosafot's point is no, no,
no, like it is to some degree no longer under your control,
it's not yours, it belongs to הקדש, hekdesh, but to some—it's not
fully. It still has this idea that it's your קרבן. korban. So
it's this like gray zone. But because it still is associated with
me, it's not a full מכירה. mechira. Okay, so very interesting, very
central in terms of thinking about הקדש hekdesh and different types of
הקדש, hekdesh, different processes, different end results, and how that would lead
to this question of paying four and five. Okay, but let's keep
it going. רבי שמעון אומר. Rabbi Shimon omer.
So now what's this רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? So if you look
back at the משנה Mishna on ע"ד עמוד ב', ayin dalet amud
bet, it's רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said if you're חייב באחריותן, chayav
b'achrayutan, this is what we just quoted, you'll pay four and five,
and if you're not חייב באחריותן, chayav b'achrayutan, you don't pay four
and five. Now what does that mean? I go ahead like I
steal it, I sanctify it, I slaughter it, if I'm חייב באחריותן,
chayav b'achrayutan, I'm going to pay four and five, like huh? Like
you understand I stole this from David here, I'm חייב chayav in
an עולה—I—I olah accepted a נדר neder of an עולה, olah, I'm
חייב chayav in an עולה, olah, I sanctify it, so now I'm
חייב chayav if I lose this קרבן. korban. Now if I slaughter
it, I'm going to have to pay you four and five? But
if I didn't have to—if I didn't have to replace it and
I slaughtered it, I wouldn't have to pay you four and five,
like there's no logic to any of that. The more I'm חייב
באחריותן, chayav b'achrayutan, the more it makes it like mine. Why in
that case when I slaughter it should I more be liable to
pay you? Okay, so that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to say.
אמרי, Amrei, says the גמרא, Gemara מהי דסבר רבי שמעון מה לי
מכר להדיוט מה לי מכר לשמים, mahi d'savar Rabbi Shimon mah li
machar l'hedyot mah li machar l'shamayim, maybe רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon holds
that הקדש—the hekdesh act of הקדש, hekdesh, forget the slaughtering, maybe he's
saying the הקדש hekdesh should make me pay the four and five,
even though like against what we said before. But if that's true,
איפכא מיבעי ליה, ifcha miba'ei lei, he should say the reverse. קדשים
שחייב באחריותן, kodashim she'chayav b'achrayutan, if I'm still liable for it, I'd
have to replace it if it gets lost, I'm
the גנב, then פטור, patur I'm exempt because that's not like a
מכירה, mechira, that's still like it's mine, דאכתי לא נפיק מרשותיה, d'achti
lo nafik me'reshutei, it didn't leave my control. קדשים שאינו חייב באחריותן,
kodashim she'eino chayav b'achrayutan, if however I wouldn't have to pay if
they got stolen or lost, in that case חייב chayav דאפקינהו מרשותיה,
d'afkineihu me'reshutei, it goes out of my control. So maybe רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon is talking about not being חייב chayav for slaughtering, maybe
he's talking about being חייב chayav for the act of הקדש. hekdesh.
But if that's true, it's more of a מכירה mechira when I'm
not חייב באחריותן, chayav b'acharayutan, when it leaves my control, what רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon said, I pay when I am חייב באחריותן, chayav
b'acharayutan, that doesn't make sense. There, it's even more under my control.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אמרי רבי שמעון אמילתא דפסיקא קאי, Amri
Rebbi Shimon amilta d'psika kai, רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon is not dealing
directly responding to our case of stealing and then sanctifying and slaughtering
and selling. He's not dealing with that case where I stole it
from the owner and it was not קדשים kodshim in the hands
of the owner. He's dealing with another scenario. והכי קתני, V'hachi katani,
and here's what it's talking about: אין הגנב אחר הגנב משלם תשלומי
ארבעה וחמשה. Ein haganav achar haganav meshalem tashlumei arba'ah v'chamishah. If you
steal from a גנב, you don't pay four and five, because it's
not מבית האיש, mibeis ha'ish, the גנב doesn't fully own it and
so on. And you don't pay the owner because it's not in
the owner's house.
Okay, וכן הגונב הקדש מבית בעלים פטור. v'chen haganav hekdesh mibeis ba'alim
patur. And not only that, if you steal a קרבן korban from
the owner, you don't pay them four and five. Okay, you got
it? So it's not I stole it and I was מקדיש makdish
it. David here was מקדיש makdish a קרבן. korban. He had an
עולה olah in his house. I stole it from him. Do I
have to pay him four and five? So the answer is no.
ומאי טעמא? U'mai ta'ama? וגונב מבית האיש—stolen V'gunav mibeis ha'ish from the
house of the owner, ולא מבית הקדש. v'lo mibeis hekdesh. Once it's
הקדש, hekdesh, that's an exemption. Okay. רבי שמעון אומר, Rebbi Shimon omer,
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says, 'Ah, no, sometimes it is considered like
David's
animal.' קדשים שחייב באחריותן, Kodshim she'chayav b'acharayutan, if David would have to
replace it if it got lost, חייב, chayav, then it is like
his animal because if he doesn't have the sheep, it's going to
cost him another sheep. So even though it's הקדש, hekdesh, it's considered
David's and therefore I do pay David four and five even though
it was הקדש, hekdesh, חייב. chayav. מאי טעמא? קרינא ביה וגונב מבית
האיש, Karina bei v'gunav mibeis ha'ish,
because it is taken from his house. It's something that he will
totally suffer the loss of this animal. ושאינו חייב באחריותן פטור, V'she'eino
chayav b'acharayutan patur, but if he's not, doesn't have to replace it,
then I'd be exempt if I stole it from him, דלא קרינא
ביה וגונב מבית האיש. d'lo karina bei v'gunav mibeis ha'ish. Okay. So
that's a good פשט of the משנה, mishna, and it does sound
like that. That רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon is a little bit tacked
on to the end of the משנה. mishna. He's not directly responding
to our case of stealing חולין, chullin, sanctifying it and slaughtering it.
He's just telling you another הלכה. halacha. Be aware that קדשים kodshim
that you're חייב באחריותן chayav b'acharayutan are like yours. And therefore, if
the גנב steals it, a קדשים kodshim from somebody's house and that
person is going to have to replace that animal, then even though
it's הקדש, hekdesh, that's a full גניבה and you pay כפל and
you pay four and five. Now we've got another question. I stole
this little עולה olah from David's house. It's considered David's. I have
to pay him כפל. Now I'm going to slaughter it. I'm going
to have to pay him four and five. We've got a little
bit of a problem, though. What happens when I slaughter this עולה
olah in my house, in my backyard?
It's אסור בהנאה. assur b'hana'ah. Yeah, it's a קרבן korban slaughtered out
of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, שחוטי חוץ, shchutei chutz, right? Which
is a classic case where רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon himself, רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon is the one who says שחוטי חוץ, shchutei chutz, you
don't pay four and five because it's שחיטה שאינה ראויה shchita she'eina
re'uyah because you can't go ahead and benefit from it, right? It's
אסור בהנאה. assur b'hana'ah. Okay, actually he said חולין בעזרה, chullin b'azarah,
this is שחוטי חוץ. shchutei chutz. Okay, but either way, רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon is the one who says that if you can't benefit
from it, you don't pay four and five.
And that's the case where you started the שחיטה shchita and then
you dragged it inside.
Right. Correct. So that was חולין בעזרה. chullin b'azarah. This is שחוטי
חוץ. shchutei chutz. This is like the flip of it. But either
way, why am I paying four and five? It's not going to
be able to be eaten. It's קדשים kodshim slaughtered out of the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says one minute.
The גמרא Gemara says, מכדי, michdi, let's take a look. שמענא ליה
לרבי שמעון, Shamana lei l'Rebbi Shimon, we know about רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon that he holds that שחיטה שאינה ראויה לא שמה שחיטה, shchita
she'eina re'uyah lo shma shchita, that if a שחיטה shchita doesn't make
it permissible to be eaten, you don't have to pay four and
five, it's not an act of slaughter. So קדשים נמי שחיטה שאינה
ראויה היא. kodshim nami shchita she'eina re'uyah hi. This case, you slaughtered
a קדשים kodshim out of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, it's a
שחיטה שאינה ראויה. shchita she'eina re'uyah. So what's the best answer? Who
said you slaughtered it outside the
בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash? Yeah! So כי אתא רב דימי אמר רבי
יוחנן בשוחט תמימים מבפנים לשם בעלים. Ki ata Rav Dimi amar Rebbi
Yochanan b'shochet tmimim mibifnim l'shem ba'alim. I steal this little sheep from
David, but then I feel so bad. So I'm going to go
ahead and it's a קרבן, korban, you know? Like I said, I
might be a גנב but I'm a פרום גנב. frum ganav. So
I bring it to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and I say,
'Here, here's David's עולה,' olah, and bring this up for the sake
of David. Okay, and therefore it's—and I, you know what? But I
say but I want to do it myself because you know what?
You don't need a כהן kohen to do שחיטה shchita by קרבנות,
korbanos, even a זר zar can do שחיטה shchita by קרבנות. korbanos.
So I bring it to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, I שחט
shacht it for David to be offered up for David. And therefore,
it's—I can eat the meat. Okay, but I have to pay him
four and five. The גמרא says one minute. If I did it
for David's sake and I brought it to the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, שהרי חזר קרן לבעלים. she'harei chazar keren l'ba'alim.
That's like I returned it to David. And the favor I brought
him his קרבן korban to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. You might
say I want to do it myself, but it's not like I'm
not חייב chayav for כפל and four and
five, right? How could an act of offering it up on his
behalf, that's effectively an act of giving it back to him? How
could that be an act of furthering the גניבה? Remember the חיוב
chiyuv for שחיטה shchita is I'm furthering the גניבה. How is that
an act of furthering the גניבה that makes me pay four and
five? Exactly. Exactly. So I'll give you the ברבי Barabbi כשנשפך הדם.
kshenishpach hadam. Okay. So what happened was is at the end of
the day though the כהן kohen spilled the blood but that was
going to be thrown on the altar. So therefore at the end
of the day it wasn't offered up on your behalf. Okay but
since at the time of the שחיטה shechitah it would have been
fit to be eaten had the blood been sprinkled okay that's going
to make it a שחיטה ראויה shechitah reuyah and I'm going to
pay four and five although at that time we would have said
that you're פטור because you were giving it back to David. Now
the blood got spilled so now we realize oh so David didn't
get it credited on his behalf so I didn't give it back
to him. So now we see it was an act of furthering
the גניבה but somehow even though in hindsight we now say it
was an act of furthering the גניבה we still have to prepare
to call it a שחיטה ראויה shechitah reuyah because at the time
which is funny could have say in hindsight now we see that
you won't be able to eat the meat but at the moment
the שחיטה shechitah was done the meat was fit to be eaten
okay because it was being brought as a קרבן korban in the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and it's and in hindsight we're going to
say and it was an act of גניבה because the blood was
spilled and it never actually got credited to David's account. Okay.
What if somebody brings an עולה olah and the priest spills the
blood? Does he have to bring another עולה? olah? Yes.
He does. If he's חייב אחריותה chayav achrayusa and if he accepted
if he made a נדר neder yeah yeah I know even though
it wasn't his fault if he made a נדר neder until that
עולה olah is brought yes.
And the כהן's kohen's not held for any responsibility?
Correct. I mean there's a גמרא that says if he does it
intentionally maybe we make the כהן kohen pay certain cases but generally
no. Okay. So the גמרא says yes otherwise you know כהנים kohanim
would all have to get this like malpractice insurance right? So the
גמרא says so okay but it's a little funny it's a little
funny that if we reassess based on the spilled blood if we
reassess based on the spilled blood that it was not an act
of returning the object we're still not going to reassess in terms
of the nature of the שחיטה shechitah we're still going to say
it was a legitimate שחיטה. shechitah. That's answer number one. Answer number
two is כי אתא רבין אמר רבי יוחנן ki ata Ravin amar
Rabbi Yochanan why make the guy such a
צדיק? tzaddik? בשוחט תמימי בפנים שלא לשם בעלים. beshocheit temimi bifnim shelo
l'shem ba'alim. I brought the קרבן korban and I said it's my
קרבן korban I stole David's עולה olah I brought it to the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and I said it's my קרבן korban so
think about what happens now. Does David get credit for it? No.
A קרבן korban brought שלא לשם בעלים shelo l'shem ba'alim he doesn't
get credit. So I didn't do I didn't give it back to
him. Was it a שחיטה ראויה? shechitah reuyah? Yes because I can
now you know the meat can now be eaten okay I mean
I guess we're assuming it's a שלמים shelamim well even though it's
a חטאת chatas the כהנים kohanim could eat the meat. I guess
we're assuming that it's not an עולה olah okay. So actually that's
an interesting question would it be a שחיטה ראויה shechitah reuyah if
it could only be burnt on the מזבח mizbeiach because at least
you could the שחיטה shechitah was effective it was effective to make
it meat that could be offered up on the מזבח. mizbeiach. I
don't know that's an interesting question and רב שמעון Rav Shimon right
well I'm not נחר nachar I'm wondering even if it's an עולה
olah maybe. It's an interesting question but well okay. Anyway but one
way or the other the meat the שחיטה shechitah was a good
שחיטה shechitah it was a שחיטת קדשים shechitas kodshim okay but because
it wasn't done on David's behalf it wasn't an act of returning
it and that's how you're able to get me have to pay
four and five to David. Okay and we'll read one more sentence
and we'll continue with this tomorrow. ריש לקיש אמר בשוחט בעלי מומין
בחוץ. Reish Lakish amar beshocheit ba'alei mumin bachutz. Okay ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish said no no no it was out of the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash but it had a מום mum in it. So if
it had a מום mum in it it had a blemish it
couldn't be brought as a קרבן. korban. If it couldn't be brought
as a קרבן korban so shechting it out of the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash okay now one minute shechting it out of the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash is not the sin of שחוטי חוץ shchutei chutz
because you're only חייב chayav for bringing a קרבן korban out of
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash if it could be brought in the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So I didn't do the biblical violation of
being שוחט shocheit a קרבן korban out of the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash if it had a blemish. But it still is שחיטה שאינה
ראויה shechitah she'einah reuyah if I haven't redeemed it if it still
has קדושה. kedusha. A
dead animal that was sanctified cannot be eaten okay it was a
dead קרבן korban something that was sanctified with קדושת קרבן kedushas korban
that was slaughtered so why is it a שחיטה ראויה shechitah reuyah
I might not have transgressed שחוטי חוץ shchutei chutz but the animal
still can't be eaten right? So we'll discuss that tomorrow but we
have three different scenarios of how shechting this קרבן korban that I
stole might still be a שחיטה ראויה shechitah reuyah the שחיטה shechitah
might be considered valid.